Shengyao Zhuang

T: (+61) 416190621 | shengyaozhuang@gmail.com | http://arvinzhuang.github.io/

PERSONAL SUMMARY

I am a postdoctoral researcher at CSIRO's Australian e-Health Research Centre, where I focus on developing large language model-based search engine systems in the medical domain. Before joining CSIRO, I was a Ph.D. student at the ielab, EECS, The University of Queensland, Australia, supervised by Professor Guido Zuccon. My primary research interests lie in information retrieval, large language model-based neural rankers, and NLP in general.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

The University of Queensland, Brisbane

Dec 2023 - Current

Adjunct Lecturer

CSIRO, Australian e-Health Research Centre, Brisbane

Mar 2023 - Current

- Postdoctoral Research Fellow
- Search and Natural Language Process for Precision Medicine.

Microsoft, Software Technology Center Asia, Beijing

May 2022 - Nov 2022

- Research Intern
- Developing multimodal and multilingual entity retrieval models.

The University of Queensland, Brisbane

Jul 2019 - May 2022

- Tutor
- Tutoring of the INFS7410 (Information Retrieval and Web Search) course. Preparing and delivering course materials, assignments, and exam marking.

The University of Queensland, Brisbane

Apr 2019 - July 2019

- Casual Research Assistant
- Assist with the research and development of methods of information retrieval and evaluation based on online learning to rank.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Computer Science

July 2019 - Dec 2023

- University of Queensland, Brisbane
- Research topic: Teaching Pre-trained Language Models to Rank Effectively, Efficiently and Robustly
- Supervisor: Professor Guido Zuccon

Master of Information Technology

Feb 2017 - Dec 2018

- University of Queensland, Brisbane
- GPA: 6.3/7

Bachelor of Electrical Engineering

Sep 2012 - Jul 2016

- Chongqing University of Science and Technology, Chongqing China
- GPA: 79.64/100

AWARDS

2021 ICTIR: Best Student Paper Award

- Effective and Privacy-preserving Federated Online Learning to Rank
- https://sigir.org/sigir2021/awards/

2021 SIGIR Top10 Authors: Rank #3 (unofficial)

- Based on normalized full paper count.
- https://groups.cs.umass.edu/zamani/2021/04/29/sigir-2021-stats/

2021 Huawei DIGIX Global Al Challenge: CHAMPION

- Search rankings in multimodal and multilingual contexts.
- As the team leader, US\$30,000 prize.
- https://developer.huawei.com/consumer/en/activity/digixActivity/Winnerlist

2022 SIGIR: Best Paper Honorable Mention

- Reduce, Reuse, Recycle: Green Information Retrieval Research
- https://sigir.org/sigir2022/program/best-paper-awards/

2022 ADCS: Best Paper Award

- Robustness of Neural Rankers to Typos: A Comparative Study
- http://adcs-conference.org/2022/index.html

PUBLICATIONS

PromptReps: Prompting Large Language Models to Generate Dense and Sparse Representations for Zero-Shot Document Retrieval

- Shengyao Zhuang, Xueguang Ma, Jimmy Lin, Guido Zuccon
- 2024, Arxiv (Under review)

Understanding and Mitigating the Threat of Vec2Text to Dense Retrieval Systems

- Shengyao Zhuang, Bevan Koopman, Xiaoran Chu, Guido Zuccon
- 2024, Arxiv (Under review)

ReSLLM: Large Language Models are Strong Resource Selectors for Federated Search

- Shuai Wang, **Shengyao Zhuang**, Bevan Koopman, Guido Zuccon
- 2024, Arxiv (under review)

A Setwise Approach for Effective and Highly Efficient Zero-shot Ranking with Large Language Models

- Shengyao Zhuang, Honglei Zhuang, Bevan Koopman, Guido Zuccon
- 2024 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2024)

Leveraging LLMs for Unsupervised Dense Retriever Ranking

- Ekaterina Khramtsova, **Shengyao Zhuang**, Mahsa Baktashmotlagh, Guido Zuccon
- Joint first author
- 2024 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2024)

Dense Retrieval with Continuous Explicit Feedback for Systematic Review Screening Prioritisation

- Xingyu Miao, **Shengyao Zhuang**, Bevan Koopman, Guido Zuccon
- 2024 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2024)

Large Language Models for Stemming: Promises, Pitfalls and Failures

- Shuai Wang, **Shengyao Zhuang**, Guido Zuccon
- 2024 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2024)

Stemming with Large Language Models: Promises, Pitfalls and Failures

- Shuai Wang, **Shengyao** Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2024 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2024)

Fed4RAG: A New Test Collection for Federated Search Augmented Generation

- Shuai Wang, Ekaterina Khramtsova, Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2024 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2024)

Zero-shot Generative Large Language Models for Systematic Review Screening Automation

- Shuai Wang, Harrisen Scells, **Shengyao Zhuang**, Martin Potthast, Bevan Koopman, Guido Zuccon
- 2024, European Conference on Information Retrieval: Findings (ECIR2024-findings)

TeachingPpre-trained Language Models to Rank Effectively, Efficiently, and Robustly

- Shengyao Zhuang
- 2023, PhD Thesis

Open-source Large Language Models are Strong Zero-shot Query Likelihood Models for Document Ranking

- Shengyao Zhuang, Bing Liu, Bevan Koopman, Guido Zuccon
- 2023, Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing: Findings (EMNLP2023findings)

Typos-aware Bottlenecked Pre-Training for Robust Dense Retrieval

- Shengyao Zhuang, Linjun Shou, Jian Pei, Ming Gong, Houxing Ren, Guido Zuccon, Daxin Jiang
- 2023 ACM SIGIR Conference on Information Retrieval in the Asia Pacific (SIGIR-AP2023)

Selecting which Dense Retriever to use for Zero-Shot Search

- Ekaterina Khramtsova, Shengyao Zhuang, Mahsa Baktashmotlagh, Xi Wang, Guido Zuccon
- 2023 ACM SIGIR Conference on Information Retrieval in the Asia Pacific (SIGIR-AP2023)

Beyond CO2 Emissions: The Overlooked Impact of Water Consumption of Information Retrieval Models

- Guido Zuccon, Harrisen Scells, Shengyao Zhuang
- 2023 ACM SIGIR International Conference on the Theory of Information Retrieval (ICTIR2023)

Exploring the Representation Power of SPLADE Models

- Joel Mackenziem, Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- Joint first author
- 2023 ACM SIGIR International Conference on the Theory of Information Retrieval (ICTIR2023)

Augmenting Passage Representations with Query Generation for Enhanced Cross-Lingual Dense Retrieval

• Shengyao Zhuang, Linjun Shou, Guido Zuccon

2023 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2023)

Bridging the Gap Between Indexing and Retrieval for Differentiable Search Index with Query Generation

- Shengyao Zhuang, Houxing Ren, Linjun Shou, Jian Pei, Ming Gong, Guido Zuccon, Daxin Jiang
- 2023 The First Workshop on Generative Information Retrieval at SIGIR2023

Implicit Feedback for Dense Passage Retrieval: A Counterfactual Approach

- Shengyao Zhuang, Hang Li, Guido Zuccon
- 2022 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2022)

CharacterBERT and Self-Teaching for Improving the Robustness of Dense Retrievers on Queries with Typos

- Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2022 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2022)

Reduce, Reuse, Recycle: Green Information Retrieval Research

- Harrisen Scells, Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2022 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2022)

Asyncval: A Toolkit for Asynchronously Validation Dense Retriever Checkpoints during Training

- Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2022 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2022)

To Interpolate or not to Interpolate: PRF, Dense and Sparse Retrievers

- Hang Li, Shuai Wang, **Shengyao Zhuang**, Ahmed Mourad, Xueguang Ma, Jimmy Lin, Guido Zuccon
- 2022 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2022)

Fast Passage Re-ranking with Contextualized Exact Term Matching and Efficient Passage Expansion

- Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2022, 1st Workshop on Reaching Efficiency in Neural Information Retrieval (ReNeuIR)

Reinforcement Online Learning to Rank with Unbiased Reward Shaping

- Shengyao Zhuang, Zhihao Qiao, Guido Zuccon
- 2022 Information Retrieval Journal (IRJ)

Pseudo Relevance Feedback with Deep Language Models and Dense Retrievers: Successes and Pitfalls

- Hang Li, Ahmed Mourad, Shengyao Zhuang, Bevan Koopman, Guido Zuccon
- 2022, ACM Transactions on Information Systems (TOIS)

Improving Query Representations for Dense Retrieval with Pseudo Relevance Feedback: A Reproducibility Study

- Hang Li, Shengyao Zhuang, Ahmed Mourad, Xueguang Ma, Jimmy Lin, Guido Zuccon
- 2022 European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR2022)

Dealing with Typos for BERT-based Passage Retrieval and Ranking

- Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2021 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP2021)

TILDE: Term Independent Likelihood model for Passage Re-ranking

- Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2021 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2021)

How do Online Learning to Rank Methods Adapt to Change of Intents?

- Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2021 ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR2021)

Effective and Privacy-preserving Federated Online Learning to Rank

- Shuyi Wang, Bing Liu, Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2021 ACM SIGIR International Conference on the Theory of Information Retrieval (ICTIR2021)

BERT-based Dense Retrievers Require Interpolation with BM25 for Effective Passage Retrieval

- Shuai Wang, **Shengyao Zhuang**, Guido Zuccon
- 2021 ACM SIGIR International Conference on the Theory of Information Retrieval (ICTIR2021)

Deep Query Likelihood Model for Information Retrieval

- Shengyao Zhuang, Hang Li, Guido Zuccon
- 2021 European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR2021)

Federated Online Learning to Rank with Evolution Strategies: A Reproducibility Study

- Shuyi Wang, Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2021 European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR2021)

Counterfactual Online Learning to Rank

- Shengyao Zhuang, Guido Zuccon
- 2020 European Conference on Information Retrieval (ECIR2020)

REFERENCES

Name: Prof. Guido Zuccon
Organisation: UQ EECS
Position: Professor
Name: Dr. Bevan Koopman
Organisation: CSIRO AEHRC
Position: Senior Research Scientist

Email: g.zuccon@uq.edu.au
Email: bevan.koopman@csiro.au